This is Software Engineering Radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SE-Radio.net.
SE Radio is brought to you by the IEEE
Computer Society and by IEEE Software
Magazine online at
computer.org/software.
Hello everyone. Welcome to this episode
of Software Engineering Radio. Our guest
today is Pete Warden. Pete is CEO of
Useful Sensors.
Pete was the founding member of the
TensorFlow team at Google and the tech
lead for all non-cloud TensorFlow
infrastructure at Google for 7 years.
Welcome Pete to the show. It's really
great to have you here. Is there
anything you'd like to add to your bio
before we get started?
No, I think that's great. Thanks so
much.
So Pete, our goal today is to explore
the reasons to and the challenges in
deploying machine learning on low-power,
small-footprint hardware. This is the
essence of TinyML, a term I understand
has been coined by you. So Pete, to
start, what is TinyML? Why is it
important?
Yeah, to start with I should say that
Evgeny Gusev of Qualcomm and me were the
coiners of TinyML and actually started
the TinyML conference series together.
So I want to make sure he gets credit.
But really the idea behind TinyML is
that being able to run machine learning
on tiny, cheap embedded devices that are
in everyday objects all around us opens
up a whole bunch of possibilities of
doing things especially around
interacting with our environment in ways
that we've never been able to before.
Can you give an example?
So one of my things I really want to be
able to do is just look at a table lamp
and say on and have the lamp come on.
And
that sounds like a straightforward task,
but actually there's a whole bunch of
technological challenges in order to
make that happen. And then on top of
those, a whole bunch of economic and
business challenges.
Before we get more into that, is tinyML
related to IoT, the Internet of Things,
or it's completely unrelated?
So, this is actually one of my bugbears
is
I really don't think that the Internet
of Things has succeeded. And the
definition that I've seen most often at
the Internet of Things is the idea that
by adding network connectivity to
everyday objects, you're going to
actually enable a whole bunch of really
exciting new things. In the same way
that adding Internet connectivity to
laptops and cell phones created
incredible innovation and change and
growth. I think that the analogy does
not hold for embedded systems and
everyday objects for a whole bunch of
reasons. And I think it's kind of misled
a lot of people to invest in adding
connectivity and then just hoping
wonderful things happen. tinyML, from my
perspective, is a lot more about saying,
"Hey, let's leave connectivity until we
need it. But let's try and make these
individual objects smarter on their own,
locally, with no Internet connection.
And let's see how far we can go with
that."
So, in your example of being able to
look at a lamp and that turning on, it
has got nothing to do with network
connectivity.
Yeah, and one of the key things with
that is you could imagine buying a lamp,
plugging it in, and then immediately
being up to talk to it and have it work,
just like you could in the old days with
any other object you bought. You didn't
have to go through setup. You didn't
have to use a phone app. You didn't have
to have an account. You didn't have to
worry about firmware updates. It's kind
of the idea of going back to objects
that just work out of the box is I think
a big part of the promise.
But there is machine learning involved.
How is this tiny ML different from
traditional machine learning?
So, I didn't know much about embedded
devices when I first joined Google. I
sort of knew that they were this
esoteric area, but I'd never had much
contact with them. When I joined Google,
one of the first people I met was Basil
Alvares, and he explained that they were
using 30 kilobyte sized models for the I
won't say the full wake word for
Google's voice assistant cuz I don't
want everybody's phones going off, but
the detection of that wake word only ran
in 30 kilobytes, and I couldn't
understand why. And so, that led me down
this path of realizing that there are
these chips that only cost 50 cents or
25 cents, but they use almost no power.
So, you can have them running for a very
long time on a battery, and they're so
cheap and low power means that they can
be in almost everything you buy. So,
there were 40 billion of these being
sold a year. So, I grew fascinated by
the constraints that were involved in
taking what is traditionally you're
looking at maybe hundreds of megabytes
for machine learning model and trying to
run it in something that may only have
as much memory as like a Commodore 64
from the '80s. And it turns out that
machine learning actually scales down
really, really well. And you can do
things not with the same accuracy, but
with enough accuracy to be useful even
in these really cheap, low-power
devices, especially things around
understanding what people are doing and
understanding the environment around
them.
So, you compared the amount of memory
with the very old hardware. How much is
it actually, the memory?
The smallest devices I've actually done
work on have had 64 KB
of RAM. And one of the design goals of
the open-source software that I worked
on at Google aimed at these kinds of
devices, the whole of the software
framework had to fit in less than 20 KB.
So, we're really talking very much kind
of 1980s
scales of memory when we're looking at
these very ubiquitous embedded devices.
So, the devices that we're looking at,
you gave an example of a lamp. What else
are we talking? Doorbells?
I mean, I would say doorbells are one of
the few places where IoT has actually
shown its potential because they tend to
be connected because you need to watch
images from afar. I would say actually,
if you look at things like coffee
machines, Keurig actually ship a little
computer vision model in a lot of their
coffee machines now that recognizes the
pods that you put in. So, that is
running locally on a very low-cost
because, you know, coffee machines are
often below 100 bucks retail. So, that
means probably you can't have more than
15, 20 dollars worth of parts in them.
So, you're looking at a very, very
low-cost piece of hardware including the
camera, but they want to be able to
offer this functionality, so they
figured out how to shrink down the
machine learning models to do this kind
of image recognition into something
that's probably only 20 cents worth of
hardware.
So, it's cheap memory you said, very,
very low, 64 KB RAM was example. What
about CPU and power consumption?
So,
it depends on the particular target
environment. Some applications really
need to run with very low power because
they need to run for a long time, and
they need to be left to run kind of
unattended with no charging or battery
changes happening. So, in those cases,
you might have something like I think
Ambiq are an example of a company that
does very low power Cortex-M MCUs, and
they might be running at 1 mW or below.
And when you get down to that low sort
of power, you're paying a little bit
more in cost. You know, it might be more
like a dollar for an MCU to get that low
power regime. And then, on the other
side, I've started to see RISC-V MCUs
with somewhere in the region of 64 KB of
memory for 10 cents on some of these
sites. So, they're not going to be using
as little power, you know, they might be
50 mW of power that they're using, but
they're incredibly cheap. You know,
you're starting to get to the point
where they're cheaper than individual
resistors and capacitors and things. So,
they start to edge out traditional
electronics when you want to build
something, you might as well just grab
an MCU.
You mentioned MCU, that's
microcontroller.
Yes, no, thank you for spelling that
out. Yes.
And is there any other type of hardware
that is used here?
So, another related piece of hardware is
digital signal processor or DSP. They
often share a lot of characteristics
with microcontroller units, but they
tend to have a lot more compute
capability. They're designed to run
doing things like audio processing and
as it turns out they're actually the
same operations that you need to do
audio processing are also very useful
for doing machine learning operations.
So these traditional DSPs are often very
good at running machine learning models
if you're able to take advantage of
them.
So traditional machine learning is
associated with big data. So how do you
actually reconcile tiny ML with the data
heavy requirements of traditional ML?
So you often still require a large
amount of data to train the models. And
in some ways you might even require more
data because you're training a model
that has no capacity to spare. You're
training a model that's as small as you
possibly can. So for a 30 kilobyte model
to recognize a wake word, you might
actually have something on the order of
a million utterances of different words
to help train the model to recognize the
ones that you want it to recognize. So
you're still using a whole bunch of GPUs
on the training side because of all of
this data throughput. The only advantage
is that because the model itself is so
small, you don't spend much compute on
the back propagation and the other parts
of the training. So it's an interesting
world and it's actually good in a way
because the lowered GPU requirements
mean that it's a lot more open
to innovators and academics and other
people who want to get involved but
don't have a million dollars to drop on
a GPU cluster like you know some of
the folks like Open AI.
So but you still need a lot of compute
to train it but you don't need a lot of
compute to run it. Is that the takeaway?
Yeah. And a lot of the compute that
you're using when you're training it is
actually just the processing of the
training data. The actual training
itself is pretty lightweight because the
models are so small, which means that
even though you're still having to deal
with big data, you're not having to
spend nearly as much as you would to
train like a large language model or
even a full-sized image recognition
model.
And then that's because of the size of
the model. Can you try to connect the
dots? Do you always start with a
small-size model as part of the training
or there's some process to reduce the
size after the training?
So, there's different schools of thought
on how to approach this. Some people
like to use techniques where they train
a large model and then they use things
like techniques in the literature known
as things like distillation or
teacher-student approaches. The general
approach that was used at Google and
that I tend to use is just starting with
an architecture of a model that only has
a few layers and only has a few weights.
And then just pushing through a lot of
data through that model and then doing
some things like quantizing down to
8-bit and a few other things like that
to just make sure that you've compressed
the model as much as you possibly can
for deployment.
As you start the process, you are aware
that this model is going to be used for
tiny ML, you need much more data to
train it, but the model size is small
and hence easier to actually more
accessible for more people to train.
Exactly. And this is one thing that's a
bit different from tiny ML compared to a
lot of traditional ML projects is you
really need to know about your
deployment platform when you're training
your model. The workflow for ML in
general is often you'll have researchers
who are using Python and PyTorch and
these other frameworks, and their job is
to just come up with a model that is as
accurate as possible. And they aren't
thinking too much about the resources
involved because accuracy is the most
important thing, and if you're running
on the cloud, you can always just buy a
bigger Amazon EC2 instance or buy a
bigger graphics card or buy more virtual
machines, and you can just pay money to
run larger models. So, those ML teams,
those researchers are able to
effectively train a model as best they
can, and then just throw over the wall
to the deployment teams, and have the
production teams worry about how they're
actually going to deploy those models.
Whereas in TinyML, you have to be
thinking about the full stack of data,
training, and deployment when you're
actually creating your model. You may
even have to think about things like,
"Oh, this particular piece of hardware
is good at doing 5 by 5 convolutions,
say, but it's not good at doing anything
larger than that." So, you actually set
up your models so that they only use the
operations in ways that are optimized
for the piece of hardware that you're
actually going to be deploying on. So,
it requires a lot more knowledge of
different layers of the whole stack, you
know, all the way from the world of
embedded tools and chips, all the way up
to PyTorch and ML frameworks, GPU
training, and data. So, in some ways
it's a lot more challenging,
but I also think it's really fun because
we get frustrated in one area, you can
always go and work on a problem in
another.
Could you maybe drill down a a bit into
the example you mentioned about being
aware of the extent of being the fact
that there's a 5 by 5 convolution. Could
you maybe just start with explaining
what's a convolution and help us picture
what the challenge is?
Yeah, definitely. So,
the way that I like to think about
neural networks and deep learning is as
these pattern recognition machines. And
a convolution is in its simplest form,
it's a square block which contains
numerical values that form a pattern.
So, if you've ever done any image
processing, you might think about trying
to recognize vertical lines by having a
5 by 5 or a 3 by 3 square block where
you have high values going down in a
vertical line through the center and
then zero values for the rest of the
block. And what happens when you take
that patch, that convolution patch, and
run it over an image kind of as a
sliding window, is that when the patch
and the underlying image match, you
basically do what's known as a
convolution, but actually it's not what
we call a convolution in classical image
processing, which is additionally
confusing. But you basically multiply
each pixel in the image against each
value in this
convolution patch, and then you add up
all the results. So, that means when
you've got this sliding window patch
that's moving across the image, if it's
got a vertical line down through the
middle, any parts of the image that have
a vertical line in that same position
will come up with a very high value. And
then the rest of the image will give a
much lower value for that patch. What
happens with neural networks, especially
in the vision side, is you don't create
those patches manually like you would
with classic image processing. Instead,
you have the network trained through
backpropagation to figure out what
patches it should use for kind of
running across the image to find
interesting things. So, one example I
like to use is if you imagine that you
were training a neural network to look
for a cat, you'd look for some low-level
features first in the kind of first
layer. So, you might say, "Hey, I've got
a patch which corresponds to kind of the
texture of fur." And you run that across
the image and you find out which parts
of the image have kind of fur in them.
And then you might also have something
that looks for kind of triangular
corners in the image as another patch.
And you run that over the image. And you
do that for maybe 64 or 128 different
patches in the first layer. And you end
up with this new image that's based on
the original image but has the results
of running those patches in sliding
windows over the image in each channel.
And the magic of neural networks is that
they start off with these very low-level
representations of, "Oh, maybe there's
fur in this corner of the image and
maybe there's like this triangular bit."
And each layer looks at the information
from the layer before and
does a similar kind of convolution, but
instead of looking for fur, you know,
the fur texture, it might say, "Hey,
anywhere where the fur value is high
in that channel, oh, and somewhere where
you've got this triangular point, then
I'm going to say that might be an ear."
So, the next layer in the neural network
has this higher-level semantic
information about what's happening in
the image, and eventually you get to the
last layer, which is able to say, "Hey,
are there
two ears, two eyes, whiskers, and fur?"
And in that case, there's probably a
high probability that there's a cat.
Now, the channels in the layers don't
actually work out to be quite that neat.
You can't say, "Oh, here's the fur
layer." Or, "Here's the ear layer." But,
conceptually, that's how the kind of
information processing works through a
neural network, if that makes sense.
And here, because you have to be
conscious that the number of layers is
small, so you have to modify the
process.
Exactly. And you have to think about
what's most important, because in the
example I used of listening out for
audio keywords to wake up a voice
assistant, because it's only 30
kilobytes,
it's not going to do as accurate a job
as something that's running even on the
main CPU on the phone, or in the cloud.
But, what it does is it wakes up the CPU
when it thinks it's found something that
might be the audio wake word. And its
job is to be okay with having false
positives, so it can be mistaken about
thinking that somebody said the wake
word when they actually didn't. Like,
that's fine, because then you'll run a
model on that same audio that's larger
on the CPU, and then maybe another one
in the cloud. And if it's not the right
phrase, those larger, more accurate
models will flag that, and the assistant
won't be activated. But, you have to be
very, very sure that you don't miss
somebody saying the wake word when they
actually said it, because in that case
that 30 kilobyte model will just give
the thumbs down and none of the larger
models will get a chance to run. So, you
have to think carefully about how this
model works within a larger system,
which is also part of the fun.
You covered that some of the challenges
and to some extent the benefit that it's
the device that is responsible for
catching all the wake words in that
example and hence definitely reduced
latency because it doesn't have to go
connect to the cloud for everything.
You know, the low power consumption also
you covered. Is there any other benefit
for on device processing?
So, privacy. You know, one of the things
that I'm pretty passionate about is you
don't have to connect your keyboard to
the internet and send all your
keystrokes up to the cloud to use it.
But at the moment that's the way that
voice interfaces work. So, it's creepy
because there's a lot of very private
personal information that's happening
and people are understandably freaked
out about the implications of this. So,
being able to run everything locally on
device
and even on a device that provably has
no internet connection like in the
example of the lamp that you control by
voice. If that doesn't have a Wi-Fi or a
Bluetooth chip in it, then you've got a
pretty good assurance that it's not
going to be used for spying on you. So,
privacy is something that I think is a
big deal here, too.
Absolutely. Privacy is certainly a very
big deal as we get into this new world.
Okay, so maybe let's take a step back
and look at different industries where
tiny ML would be most impacted. Do you
have some examples, specific use cases?
Yeah, so
honestly, one of the challenges with
tiny ML is that there's a lot of
engineering and academic and research
technologist excitement about it, but
it's been over 5 years now and it's been
slow to be adopted in a lot of the
industries where it can have the most
impact. Now, having said that, some of
the things that I've seen have been
around the idea of actually using tiny
ML in agriculture.
So, for spotting pests or spotting
disease using tiny cheap sensors that
can be kind of scattered throughout a
field or in a kind of crop storage area
to detect when there's pests and things
actually coming in. There's also been a
lot of use cases around medical devices.
So, having something that is actually
able to run for a long time on a battery
to do monitoring of various vital
statistics and look at the patterns to
understand what's actually happening
with your body and kind of raise an
alert if something significant is going
wrong. But, one of the challenges in
this area is that we don't have enough
of these stories yet. So, there's a lot
of
possibilities for really important
things that we can do here, but the
adoption has not been as fast as I think
any of us would have hoped.
What are the different sensors that are
integrated into these devices?
So, often the most important sensors are
cameras,
small CCD sensors that can be as little
as 10 cents each, and microphones, which
also can be, you know, in the single
digit cents for kind of a low cost low
end microphone. And what's interesting
about these is
you can actually figure out a lot of
stuff of what's happening in the world
around you using vision and using audio.
So, for example, you might not think of
cameras and microphones as weather
sensors, but if you're actually able to
hear raindrops or if you're actually
able to see rain happening or snow or
other kind of things like that, then
you're able to use these universal
sensors almost to find out all sorts of
other things that are happening in the
proximity of these embedded devices.
Now, there are a lot of other sensors
that come in, you know, temperature,
vibration,
accelerometers, for example, like one of
my favorite use cases
is detecting car crashes with phones.
So, you actually have the accelerometer
running all the time, and if it detects
a sharp change in acceleration, then
that gets flagged by an ML model that's
running because it can't run on the CPU
because it would drain the battery
almost immediately. So, it has to run on
this sensor hub, which is essentially a
microcontroller or DSP sitting in the
phone that uses very little power. But
the interesting thing about that use
case is it uses the accelerometer to
detect crash, but the accelerometer
readings for a crash, a car crash, are
very similar to dropping your phone. So,
it actually also uses the microphone
to see if there's sounds associated with
the car crash to make sure that it isn't
just calling emergency services because,
you know, you dropped your phone in the
bathroom.
So, it's a combination of sensors.
Exactly. This idea of sensor fusion, but
really being able to use
ML models to do this understanding of
this raw data.
So, you've got this stream of audio as
16 kHz samples coming in, and if you
just stare at the audio waveform, like
traditionally, there's nothing you could
really do with that. But, using ML
models, you can say, "Hey, was there a
car crash?" You know, "Were there sounds
of a car crash?" and get a pretty
reliable answer back. So, that's really
the big change that's happening here.
You mentioned that there's many
applications you can think of for
agriculture, for healthcare, but there
has not yet been an adoption. I was
reading about Useful Sensors, and that's
your company, the offline translation
tools. And that certainly struck a chord
with me because of a recent trip to
Italy, where trying to use translation
tools is good, but pretty hard and
clunky. So, I was very interested in the
translation tool that Useful Sensors has
developed. Can you talk more about it?
Yeah, so one of the things that I found
as well, like going abroad, and even
being in the US, and having a, you know,
a very large Spanish-speaking
population,
I'm cut off from a lot of people
because I can't speak their language.
And I love Google Translate, like it's a
technological marvel, but it's also it
hasn't evolved a massive amount
over the last, you know, sort of decade
or so. And it's also a fairly clunky
experience. You have to kind of speak
into your phone and kind of hand it
over, and you know, handing over your
phone is kind of this weird experience.
So,
really the dream was, can we make
something that's a really fluent
experience? I like to say,
talking to a person in a foreign
language should be as easy as watching a
movie
with subtitles in a different language.
And, you know, that's not something you
can do with Google Translate. If you try
to use Google Translate to watch a
movie, it would just be extremely tough.
And the other side of this as well is
you really want something that will work
anywhere in the world.
And you want that privacy
for these conversations. So,
it was a really good use case for this
idea of running machine learning
locally. Now, it's actually getting a
bit away from the TinyML roots because
I'm not running this on a
microcontroller or DSP, but actually
running it on a Cortex-A,
like the kind of SOC that you'd find in
a phone. So, it's a lot higher power,
you know, it's
like $20 instead of $0.20, but a lot of
the same principles about running
everything locally with no network
connection still apply. And, you know, I
think that I'm not happy that we've
reached our goals yet, but it's been
really great to be able to put these
devices in front of people and have
something that's on the table,
but still allowing people to have a
conversation like we're having without
having to
pause and feel like you're really in
this kind of awkward flow. Being able to
talk fluently
between two people who don't share a
language, I just think that's really
cool.
You said not as low-powered hardware as
you would like and not as cheap as you
would like, but it's still a model
that's running on device.
Exactly, with no network connection.
And what was the size of the model?
So, that's actually a lot of the work
we've put in is in the speech-to-text
side of things. So, actually taking in
the audio of all audio and actually
figuring out what people are saying as
text strings. And we've open-sourced
the models that we've developed as
Moonshine. And those models, the
smallest one is about 26 million
parameters, and the larger one is 59
million parameters. So, we quantize
everything down to 8 bits. So, that's
like 26 megabytes for the smaller model
that does this, and then 59 megabytes
for the larger model, which is a little
bit more accurate.
Now, playing the devil's advocate about
the comment about privacy, that the
processing is on device, but these
devices are also more ubiquitous. And
how do you balance that with
the fact that they're not sending the
data to the cloud, but of course they
could, right?
Yeah, and
this is part of part of my struggle is
that I'm
essentially advocating for putting
cameras and microphones in everything.
And that's a super creepy world, if you
think about it, which has led me to
think very hard about, okay, how can we
actually safeguard ourselves in this
world? How can we avoid creating this
world where we're setting things up so
everything can spy on us?
And one of the things I really want to
see is essentially a nutrition info
label
for
all devices to say what data they're
actually gathering. And in the example
of the lamp, you could have a little
label that's saying, "Hey, we're
listening to audio, but we're never
recording it. That we don't have the
capability to send it up to the cloud."
And
if then somebody discovered that, "Oh,
actually there was a Wi-Fi chip
and it was being used to transmit data,
then it's kind of like, you know, if you
were selling toothpaste that had an
ingredients list that, you know, just
had a list of nice things, but you're
actually putting, you know, sawdust in
it.
And you just hadn't listed it on the
ingredients, then the companies that
were actually doing that malicious
behavior could be called out and
prosecuted and everything else. So, I
think it's this combination of trying to
have labels that tell people
what's going to happen to their data
and having systems that make it the
easiest way is to have your data
never be transmitted, never be stored,
and just go away immediately. Like, make
that the most easy engineering and
product solution so that people aren't
tempted to cut corners and build these
insecure systems.
Now, let's get into a little bit about
what does it take for someone to develop
these applications? Starting with what
are the most popular frameworks and how
do they help?
Yeah, that's a good question. There are
a whole bunch of really interesting
solutions from chip manufacturers
themselves. So, if you look at NXP,
STMicro,
um, all of the major microcontroller and
DSP manufacturers have proprietary tools
that let you take models from
popular frameworks like PyTorch and
convert them down into their own
frameworks proprietary formats. The
problem with those is that there are so
many different models that you can
potentially create in training
frameworks
and the conversion tools are only able
to handle quite a small subset of those.
So, it can be hard to actually get all
the way through that process.
The framework that I
put together when I was at Google is
called TensorFlow Lite Micro, and it's
designed to be a cross-platform
solution for running ML models on really
tiny machines. And so, it does things
like it never uses any memory
allocation. Everything is kind of
pre-allocated. So, that's often an
important requirement for embedded
hardware or for embedded system
software. And it also doesn't rely on
any of the C runtime library.
So, printf can take up 25 kilobytes of
code space.
So,
making sure that we never call things
like printf is really important for
having something that will fit in kind
of 20 kilobytes of program space. The
best way to get models in into
TensorFlow Lite Micro is to export them
from TensorFlow. Now, TensorFlow
honestly is a bit long in the tooth
these days. You know, I think we're
coming up to its 10th anniversary. And
so, you know, I tend to use PyTorch
these days for my day-to-day work.
But, there are still a lot of resources
where you can start with TensorFlow
models. You can find a lot of the
popular models that are in TensorFlow
format, and then actually convert them
down to TensorFlow Lite Micro and run
them there. Honestly, what I usually
recommend to people getting started is
you find some examples that do something
similar to what you want to do,
like doing an audio recognition, dealing
with accelerometer data, or doing image
recognition. And you take some of those
open-source examples and get them
working on your device, and then
actually try and customize them and
retrain the models and change things to
work as you as you want to. I would say
as well, these are all available for
Arduino
and for the RP2040
and 2350 from Raspberry Pi. So, you can
run them on most of the popular
platforms.
Is Arduino a microcontroller or what
would you call it?
So, Arduino is a software framework and
a family of microcontroller boards
that are designed to be
very accessible for everyday users who
aren't necessarily embedded systems
engineers. So, they're one of the best
ways I've found for actually getting
into this kind of embedded space without
losing your mind, honestly.
So, if I wanted to be an embedded
systems engineer developing tinyML
applications, do I wear two hats, which
is training the model with an idea of
where it's going to be used and hence
the size constraints, and also for the
deployment of the model and, you know,
put possibly retraining and running
inference? Do I wear both hats or are
there two people on two roles here?
So,
it depends, but if there are two people
or three people or four people, they
really need to be working very, very
closely together. So, one of my favorite
groups at Google was the team that put
together MobileNet, which is one of the
most popular small models out there for
doing image recognition. And what was
great about them was they actually had,
like Andrew Howard, who is the
researcher and the architect of the
model, he was working in the same group,
in the same team, in the same room as
people who are writing the runtime code,
like the inner loops of the, you know,
kind of assembler that was going to
execute these models, and working with
the people who gathered the data, and
they had this small team that was
vertically integrated, so that, you
know, the person who's writing the inner
loops of the assembler could be talking
to Andrew, and could give him advice on
what operations and attributes the model
should have to run optimally
on the actual frameworks and the
hardware that they're going to be
deploying on. And kind of like vice
versa, you get this really, really
productive exchange of ideas and
requirements in a way that just isn't
possible in any other sense.
But ideally, to develop TinyML
applications, one needs to learn machine
learning and embedded systems
engineering. Is that correct, or would
you put it in a different way?
So, if you put it like that, it sounds
like you can't do anything until you've
learned both of those. The way I would
think about it is you can get started
with recipes that don't, you know, code
examples and tutorials that don't expect
you to understand much of either
embedded systems or ML. And then, the
way I always learn is by getting
something running, and then kind of like
looking under the hood, and starting to
tinker with stuff, and like seeing what
happens. And I found that to be a really
great way to for me to learn, and a lot
of the students that I work with to
actually learn. So, don't feel like you
have to get all of this knowledge before
you start doing this stuff. You can get
something running like a a wake word
detector, or a simple image recognition
model just by following, you know, a set
of directions and then you can start to
modify things, to change things, and
like learn what happens
in a very hands-on way. And that's one
of the things that I like most about
this this combination and the you know,
TinyML. When you're doing just machine
learning, traditionally that's a very
mathematical kind of almost kind of
abstract
thing where you're you're not actually
training
full models yourself. You're kind of you
fine-tuning or you know, you're
and you're a long way away from the
actual end application.
And the same with embedded systems, you
might learn a lot about the low-level
system, but you're kind of
not getting to work on kind of
cutting-edge cool problems very often.
Whereas TinyML, you get all of this
wonderful stuff that's happening in the
AI world is super relevant and you get
to learn about it. But you're also
actually putting stuff out in the world
and having people use and play with the
results of what you've done in a very
kind of way that you can hold in your
hand, which I love.
And that's why you brought up Arduino.
Yes, exactly. Like that's something that
I've seen be great for students and high
school kids and all of these people who
might not get into machine learning as
this kind of abstract thing, but if you
can build
a little robot that you can give voice
commands to, that is a lot more concrete
and tangible and kind of brings in a
much wider audience of people and is a
way of showing that machine learning
doesn't have to be this off-putting,
daunting thing to jump into. It can be
this really
fun, playful
world that I really honestly believe
anybody can actually start to learn
about.
Let's say I follow your practical advice
and I get to that level. What should I
do beyond that to improve my skills and
develop real-world applications? What
all do I have to learn in the world of
model quantization, transfer learning,
knowledge distillation? If you can
explain these terms and talk about how
do I get to that level?
Yeah, definitely. And
as you say, I think the starting point
is to pick real-world applications and
to pick something you care about. And
then I find the best way is to kind of
pick up those techniques as you go. So,
for quantization,
it's this idea that you know, I talked
about those convolution patches that you
run across the image. By default, each
one of the values in the convolution
patch would be a 32-bit floating-point
value. And so would the underlying
pixels that it's operating on. Uh now,
it turns out cuz if you imagine that,
you know, that vertical line example
that I gave, you probably don't need 32
bits of precision to be able to
represent that pattern in a way that's
effective. And it turns out that if you
encode the values in things like the
convolution patch, you know, what we
call the weights as 8 bits, and you just
use a linear encoding, so you say, "Hey,
I'm going to store what the minimum
floating-point value of this whole patch
was and the maximum floating-point value
of this whole patch." And then for each
value within the patch, I'm going to
find the 0 to 255 kind of coded value
that's closest to the floating-point
value if you kind of linearly scale
between that min max, then
you really don't lose any accuracy
in the models, or you lose a very, very
tiny amount. And And that helps the
models get smaller if you're worried
about kind of memory size. But the
really fun thing is if you then take the
activation layers or the underlying
image that that convolution is working
on, and you convert those 32-bit
floating point values into 8-bit values.
Then instead of doing 32-bit float by
32-bit float multiply adds, which is
effectively what you're doing when
you're putting the convolution patch
over each section of the image, you can
actually do 8-bit by 8-bit integer math,
which
is exactly what a lot of digital signal
processors have traditionally been
designed for, because that's an
operation you need to do a lot in signal
processing, and is a lot less expensive
to implement in silicon in terms of
power and latency than full
floating-point
implementations of like 32-bit
floating-point.
So, quantization helps you both shrink
the amount of memory and file size you
need for these models,
but also makes the math a lot easier to
implement on these microcontrollers that
may well not even have floating-point
hardware. So, quantization is at the
heart of a lot of these techniques that
we use to be able to take these large
models and actually get them running on
this very constrained hardware. And now,
I'm glad you mentioned transfer learning
as well, because that's one of my
favorite hacks in the world of machine
learning. And the basic idea is, if you
think of a image recognition model, for
example, that you've trained to
recognize, say, a thousand different
animals. So, everything from penguins
to, you know, to zebras to aardvarks,
that model,
like I was saying in the example of cat
recognition, it's going to figure out a
lot of stuff like, "Hey, I know how to
recognize ears. I know how to recognize
fur. I know how to recognize eyes and
hooves and horns and things like that."
Just because that selection of a
thousand animals has all of those
features in them and the model has to
kind of recognize different combinations
of them to tell which animal it is. Now,
if you come along with an animal that's
not included
in that original thousand animals that
you trained on, it's likely that that
animal's features have a lot in common
with some of the other animals that were
in that original training set. So, it
probably has ears, fur, you know, might
have hooves, might have horns. And what
that means is you
can chop off the very last layer
of the model because
if you think about the increasing levels
of kind of semantic information that
you're operating on as you kind of go
through the network, that very last
layer is the one that says, "Oh, have
you got two ears, fur, whiskers and you
don't have hooves, then you might be a
cat." If you get rid of that and you
instead
put in a completely untrained layer,
but you keep all of the previous layers
intact, so all of the information about,
"Hey, are there hooves, ears?" All of
this stuff still comes through, but then
that last layer, you have maybe a couple
of new animals that you throw in the
mix. You know, you might have maybe like
a a monkey and a buffalo that weren't
originally included and you then train
on a much smaller amount of data.
Like you might have thousands of images
of the original animals, but you might
only have tens of images of the buffalo
and the, you know, the monkey. It turns
out that you can train that final layer
very accurately with much less data by
using everything that it's learned from
identifying all of these other animals
in the big training run. And this is a
principle that applies across many, many
different machine learning models. So,
if you have a model that can recognize a
particular word that you've trained on
massive amounts of data on that word, if
you want to recognize a different word,
then you can often freeze most of the
layers, just kind of retrain the final
layer, and get it to recognize other
words with much less work. So, that's
one of the key techniques of this kind
of tiny ML world, is take a model that
works on a similar problem to the one
you're facing, and then just gather a
small amount of data, and try and do
transfer learning.
So, beyond this getting the model to the
right size and quantize, is there
something beyond that that is required
to have it run on this embedded device
and perform inferences?
So,
as well as the right size, the other
thing that you have to think about is
what is the latency? Because these
devices often don't have, well, they
will not have as much compute as an
Nvidia GPU. One of the pleasant
surprises is that they actually, even
very cheap devices,
maybe running at
hundreds of megahertz and have SIMD
instructions on them. So, you can
actually do hundreds of millions of
operations, arithmetic operations per
second. So, you might be surprised at
what kind of latency you can get on
these pieces of hardware. And one of the
things I've talked about is this idea of
dark compute.
That we've ended up with all of these
toasters
with incredible amounts of arithmetic
compute available, but all they're doing
is lighting up a couple of LEDs and
noticing when somebody presses a button.
So, one of the things I like about ML is
it's tiny amount as it's a way of
actually putting some of that compute
that's not being used to use.
But, you do have to think about, okay,
how much latency can I get? You know,
with an image recognition model,
it might be that it takes
a second to run, or it might be that it
takes 10 seconds to run. And you've got
to think about your application about
whether that actually works for you. You
know, if you want lights to come on
when you talk to your lamp, you don't
want the lights to come on 10 seconds
after you said it, because then you
might as well just walk over and like
hit the switch. But, there are other
applications, like if you're detecting
pests in a field, like you can take a
minute to run that, because you're
probably only running that image
recognition like once an hour or
something, like waking up the device and
running it. And there's no particular
urgency in how fast you need to get
results back. So, latency is the other
big issue, but what I like is you can
often find applications that can
tolerate pretty high latency.
We'll talk about that now, but before we
do that, you did use the acronym SIMD as
you were talking. I don't want to end
this section without you just explaining
that to our listeners.
Yes, sorry, I should have explained
that, but it's single instruction
multiple data, and it's this idea that
you can have a single CPU instruction
that instead of just operating on a
single,
you know, 32-bit value, say, integer
value or floating-point value, you
actually say, "Hey, I'm going to do this
same operation across this set of
values, like four or eight or 16 values
at a time
by running this single instruction." And
it's a really good fit for neural
networks because if you think about
that, going back to that convolution
patch example, you want to run an entire
row
of that convolution patch against an
entire row of pixels. So, if you have a
SIMD instruction that's able to kind of
do that in a single instruction and
execute it in a single cycle, then you
can actually get through a lot more
operations a lot more quickly than if
you're relying on more traditional
computing approaches.
I do notice that as I'm trying to wrap
up now to give our listeners some
pointers for things they can use to
learn more. I found a blog post, a book
that you've written, and also an
excellent course on Harvard. Are those
Did I cover all of it?
Yes, you did, though I will send you a
link to cuz I've been teaching at
Stanford
how to run models on the Raspberry Pi
for the last years. And I actually have
I'm hoping to put these together into
more of an organized, you know, possibly
a small ebook, but I actually have some
examples of doing some of the things
we've talked about up on GitHub as the
class assignments that I give our
students when I'm teaching. So, I'll
send you a link to those, and they're a
little less polished than some of the
other stuff out there, but I'm looking
to get feedback, so I'd love to hear
what people think.
We'll certainly put all of this in the
show notes. Peter, is there anything
today that we missed that you'd like to
cover?
No, I think this was really fun, really
interesting questions, and I would say I
always love hearing from people as
they're diving into this world. So, feel
free to, you know, get in touch if you
have further questions.
How can people get in touch with you?
So, my email is pete@petewarden.com.
Uh you can find my blog at
petewarden.com, where you can find all
the details on how to get hold of me.
So, yeah, love to hear from you.
Thank you. We'll put all that in the
show notes as well. And thank you so
much for joining us today.
Thank you, too.
Thanks, everyone, for listening.
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE Software Magazine. For more about
the podcast, including other episodes,
visit our website at SE-Radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, or
through our Slack channel at
SE-Radio.slack.com.
You can also email us at
team@se-radio.net.
This and all other episodes of SE Radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
License 2.5.
Thanks for listening.